<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ippos pyrros = The red horse· or The bloodines of vvar, represented in a sermon (to perswade to peace) preached at Pauls, July 16. 1648, at five of the clocke in the afternoone. / By Jo: Geree, M.A. and pastor of St Faiths under Pauls. And now published to cleare the preacher from malignancy imputed to him by some left-eared auditors.</title>
            <author>Geree, John, 1601?-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E458_28</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871916</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162107</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162107)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 73:E458[28])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ippos pyrros = The red horse· or The bloodines of vvar, represented in a sermon (to perswade to peace) preached at Pauls, July 16. 1648, at five of the clocke in the afternoone. / By Jo: Geree, M.A. and pastor of St Faiths under Pauls. And now published to cleare the preacher from malignancy imputed to him by some left-eared auditors.</title>
                  <author>Geree, John, 1601?-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for George Latham, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Bishops-head in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First two words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 16.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>War --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162107:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΙΠΠΟΣ ΠΥΡΡΟΣ THE RED HORSE. OR THE Bloodines of War, Repreſented in a Sermon (To perſwade to PEACE) Preached at PAULS, <hi>July</hi> 16. 1648, at five of the clocke in the afternoone.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Jo: Geree,</hi> M.A. and Paſtor of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Faiths</hi> under PAULS.</p>
            <p>And now publiſhed to cleare the Preacher from Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy imputed to him by ſome left-eared Auditors.</p>
            <q>Am I therefore become your enemy becauſe I tell you the truth, <bibl>Gal. 4.16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Oculis aegris odioſa eſt lux, quae puris eſt amabilis. <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Latham,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Signe of the <hi>Biſhops-head</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:162107:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:162107:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull, the Maſter, the Wardens, the Aſsiſtants, and the reſt of the worthy Company of Stationers, Grace, and Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing put upon it to Print this Sermon (as you may ſee in the Appendix thereof) I began to caſt in my mind to find out, according to the cuſtome, ſome fit Perſon to whom I might dedicate it: And remembring a curteſie lately done (at my motion) by your Company, I reſolved to teſtifie my reſpect, and thankfulneſſe for that deſerving act, by this uſuall expreſsion of gratitude. The Society of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and uſefull Colledge at <hi>Dublin</hi> being like to be diſolved for want of bread, to the great prejudice of Religion, and griefe of the truly religious; I was entreated by one of the
<note place="margin">* The Right Reverend Dr <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher.</hi> A. A.</note> prime ornaments of that Society to endeavour to promote ſome Charitable contribution, for ſome ſmall ſupport to keepe that Society together till this Nation might be in a circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to make ſuch proviſion for it as ſuch a worke did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; In which good worke while I was acting, I was by a Citizen (a great lover of Learning) directed to make my addreſſe to the Companies of <hi>London,</hi> as the likelieſt way to get ſome ſpeedy, and conſiderable ſupply: which advice of his I preſently began to put in prastice, in procuring the Maſter of your company (wherein I had moſt acquaintance and intereſt)
<pb facs="tcp:162107:3"/>to move this charitable worke with you, which he did with that ſucceſſe, that he obtained ſudainly a conſiderable gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity (the low ebbe of your Company at that time being weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) towards it, your Society concluding that it was ſuteable to them to go before others in the reliefe of a Colledge, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than expect others to be precedents to them. To expreſſe my ſence of your worth in this freeneſſe, and forwardneſſe, in ſo choiſe an Act of Charity, I have preſumed on this Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And I was yet further incited to this, by the intent of Printing this Sermon, for it is a vindication of my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency againſt ungrounded Calumny; and in whoſe opinion ſhould I rather deſire to ſtand right than in yours? To a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part of whom God hath made me Paſtor, and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher to you all, the peculiar Sermons to your Company being to be Preached by me ſo long as providence continues my intereſt in the Church of St. <hi>Faiths,</hi> where they are to be Preached; And Sermons find acceptance much according to the eſteeme of the Preacher, on their acceptance depend their efficacy, and therefore it behoved me, that no ſiniſter conceit of me ſhould by any meanes be bred and reſt in your breaſts; So hoping that this office of love will neither be ſtrange, nor unwelcome, with my Prayers for you, I take my leave, and remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Study in <hi>Ivy</hi> Lane, <date>
                     <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt 3. 1648.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your ingaged Friend and Servant in the Lords worke, JOHN GEREE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:162107:3"/>
            <head>THE RED HORSE: OR, THE BLOODINES OF WAR, Repreſented in a Sermon to perſwade to PEACE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rev. 6.4.</bibl> And there went out another horſe that was red, and power was given him that ſate thereon to take peace from the earth, and that they ſhould kill one another, and there was given unto him a great Sword.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. The Introduction to the Text.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He deareſt of Gods Children are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from ſufferings: for if they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhould not need them for refining, yet the truth needs them for ſealing, and they muſt ſuffer to ſeale the truth which they teach, and profeſſe. And yet God ceaſes not to be good to them; for <hi>when their troubles abound for Chriſt, their conſolations abound in Chriſt.</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:162107:4"/>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4. Nay, they never have more inlargements of the inward man by grace, then when moſt reſtrained in the outward man by unjuſt violence; was not <hi>David</hi> inſpired with the ſweeteſt Pſalmes in his bittereſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes? And here you ſee Saint <hi>Iohn under baniſhment in the Iſle Patmos for the teſtimony of Ieſus, Rev.</hi> 1.9, 10. was bleſt and graced with this excellent Propheſie touching the ſtate of the Chriſtian Church.</p>
               <p>Of which Propheſie you have a generall Preface, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1, 2. Seven excellent divine Epiſtles to the ſeven famous Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> wherein is not only contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned moſt uſefull inſtructions, but (as ſome thinke) a Type of the State of the Chriſtian Church to the end of the world. Afterward there is a particular Preface to the Viſion in hand, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. Then the viſion of a Book ſealed with ſeven Seales, with great ſorrow for want of one to open it, which ſorrow was allayed by the <hi>Lyon of the Tribe of Iudah, who was found worthy and able to open the Booke, and looſe the ſeven Seales of it:</hi> for which the foure Beaſts, and the twenty foure Elders ſung unto him a new Song of praiſe and thankſgiving, <hi>Cha.</hi> 5. Thirdly, there is the opening of the Seales, with the ſeverall events following, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. The firſt Seale being opened, <hi>A white horſe was ſeen, and he that ſate on him had a bow, and a Crowne was given unto him, and he went forth conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to conquer.</hi> A lively type of truth prevailing, and the ſetling of the Goſpell with power notwithſtanding all the bandying of the world <hi>againſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt, Pſal.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 6. But not long after another Seale is opened, and Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> being awakened to atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, beheld as you have heard in the Text read, <hi>And there went out another horſe that was red,</hi> &amp;c. which words I ſhall firſt endeavour to open, and then gather and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:162107:4"/>handle ſome obſervations, as God ſhall inable, and the time permit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. The opening of the Text.</head>
               <p>For the opening the ſenſe of theſe words which are plainly allegoricall, we muſt firſt remember a rule in Divinity, that <hi>in Allegoricall Texts, the meaning of the alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory is the literall ſence of the place.</hi> Now that we may find out the meaning of this Allegory, it will be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that we enquire; Firſt, <hi>what is imported by the horſe.</hi> Secondly, <hi>what by his colour, a red horſe.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>who is meant by his rider?</hi> Fourthly, <hi>what is meant by his worke?</hi> Fifthly, <hi>and what by his qualification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>What is imported by the viſion of an horſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Horſe is a ſwift and warlike creature, fitted to breake through oppoſition, and ſpeedily to execute deſignes, and therefore (I beleeve) horſes are not only wittily, but ſollidly conceived to be uſed in theſe Types to hint, that maugre the oppoſition that men or devills can make, Gods deſignes ſhall be ſpeedily, and irreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtably executed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Why was this horſered, what doth this colour import?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this colour Interpreters generally agree <hi>Bloud</hi> is meant; for <hi>Bloud</hi> is red, and it dyes red that which it toucheth or lights on, and ſo it is uſed in other places to repreſent <hi>bloud. Who is this that commeth with dyed gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from Bozrah, &amp;c. Wherefore art thou redinthine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, &amp;c. I have troden the winepreſſe alone, and of the people there was none with me, for I will tread them in mine anger, and trample them in my fury, and their bloud ſhall be ſprinkled on my garments, and I will ſtaine all my rayment. Iſa.</hi> 63.1, 2, 3. Here red doth evidently import Bloud, but the greateſt difficulty is <hi>what bloud is here meant; Paraeus</hi> by bloud here underſtands the bloud of Saints
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:162107:5"/>ſhed in Martyrdome; <hi>Equus rufus eſt Eccleſia rubens martyriis: The red horſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the Church dyed red with martyrdome; which</hi> Lyra <hi>ſeemes to reſtraine to that Christian bloud which was drawne by</hi> Nero, but this <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> diſlikes as too narrow, and therefore <hi>extends it to the bloud of the ten perſecutions,</hi> and concludes, <hi>Haec eſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis interpretatio minimè incommoda; This is the common interpretation no waies inconvenient.</hi> But our learned Countryman <hi>Brightman</hi> is of another opinion, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting this red colour to import <hi>bloud, but the bloud of war; Igneus iſte color bellum, pugnas, cades, ſanguinem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignat, &amp;c. That fiery colour doth import War, Conflicts, Slaughters, Bloud;</hi> and he is ſeconded by another learned and godly Countryman of ours, <hi>Gyffard: This repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the bloudy wars, tumults, and cruell ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the earth;</hi> and to the opinion of theſe do I incline, for the reaſons of <hi>Brightman</hi> ſeeme to me cogent: For firſt, this bloud that was to be ſhed, was to be by <hi>taking away peace from the earth. Earth</hi> we know is oppoſed to <hi>heaven,</hi> and in this booke ſaith <hi>Brightman; Coelum veram ſanctanique Eccleſiam denotat, Terra contra ſignificat im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium mundum. Heaven notes out the true and holy Church, but the earth ſignifies the wicked world.</hi> Now the bloud be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be ſhed by taking peace from the <hi>earth,</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes the <hi>world,</hi> he gathers, the ſlaughter is by <hi>War,</hi> not by <hi>perſecution,</hi> which takes away peace from the <hi>Church,</hi> not the <hi>world.</hi> He addes that this is further manifeſted by the declaration of the power given, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>and that they ſhould kill one another mutually or reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procally,</hi> but the Church revengeth not her ſelfe on her enemies, much leſſe is ſhe tranſported with rage of ſlaughtering her own; no, that is the ſtain, guilt, and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our times, to be bewailed with teares of bloud;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162107:5"/>he therefore rationally concludes, that this <hi>bloud</hi> that dies <hi>red</hi> is not to be underſtood <hi>Deperſecutione, ſed de bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum tempestate, not of a tempeſt of perſecution falling on the Church, but of war on the world.</hi> And this is laſtly confirmed by events, for in the daies of <hi>Antoninus Verus,</hi> after the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> had been long quiet from any remarkeable war: for their rejecting and perſecuting the Goſpell of peace, <hi>Pax aufertur hominibus illico,</hi> and <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ardent bellis, peace is taken from men, and all are on fire with warre.</hi> Firſt, the <hi>Perſian,</hi> and next the <hi>Marco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannian war,</hi> which was one of the foreſt the <hi>Romans</hi> had met with; compared by <hi>Eutropius</hi> to the <hi>Carthagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> war, which brought <hi>Rome</hi> to her loweſt ebbe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>But who is meant by the Rider?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paraus</hi> thinks it probable to be <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whoſe Goſpell not of it ſelfe, but accidentally through the corruption of men takes away peace; <hi>Thinke not that I am come to ſend peace on the earth: I came not to ſend peace but a ſword. Mat.</hi> 10.34. Others underſtand it of <hi>Nero,</hi> others ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to all the <hi>authors of the ten perſecutions,</hi> but theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>bloud</hi> to be the <hi>bloud of Martyrs,</hi> not of <hi>war;</hi> Others interpret this <hi>Rider</hi> to be the <hi>Devill himſelfe;</hi> So <hi>Gyfford</hi> in his Paraphraſticall Sermons on the place, <hi>The Rider upon this horſe is the devill himſelfe: for he is moſt fit for ſuch a turne, he is a cruell murtherer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp;c.</hi> And no doubt but he is the prime ſtickler or inſtigator in all ſuch bloudy deſignes, and therefore we muſt underſtand it of him, or of the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Marcomanni</hi> inſtigated by him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>What is meant by his worke?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is twofold: <hi>Power was given him to take away peace from the earth;</hi> that is, to throw a ball of contention among men, to interrupt their tranquillity, and hurry
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162107:6"/>them into a bloudy war; but marke, <hi>power was given him for this, quia non rem gereret ſuo arbitrio, ſed alieno imperio,</hi> to ſhew <hi>that he did not mannage the matter after his owne arbitrement, but at the command of another;</hi> he had had no power, had it not <hi>been given him from above,</hi> but then he could ſet all on a flame; <hi>And that they ſhould kill one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> this is plaine: peace is taken away by war, and in war mens worke is mutuall ſlaughter.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>But what is laſtly meant by the great ſword?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Paraeus <hi>underſtands it of the ſword of the Spirit, the Word of God, which doth accidentally by ſeparation made in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting ſome, not others, and by ſharpe reproofes irritate men againſt the Church;</hi> but this ſuppoſeth the <hi>bloud</hi> here to be the <hi>bloud</hi> of <hi>perſecution</hi> which being above manifeſted to be the <hi>bloud</hi> of <hi>war.</hi> This <hi>great ſword</hi> muſt needs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that power that was given by confederacies, and all requiſites of ſlaughter, by the providence of God to thoſe that ſhould be Actors in this Tragedy. And ſo you have the meaning of the words.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. The diviſion of the Text, with the ſeverall obſervations ariſing from it.</head>
               <p>In the words thus opened you have repreſented 1. an <hi>Horſe;</hi> 2. <hi>His colour red;</hi> 3. <hi>His Rider;</hi> 4. <hi>His worke, to take away peace from the earth,</hi> amplified with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent of it, <hi>that men might kill one another;</hi> 5. <hi>His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>power was given him;</hi> 6. <hi>His furniture, there was given unto him a great ſword.</hi> Many uſefull ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations are held forth to us in theſe words, I will only name ſome of them, and inſiſt on two with reference to the time.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, then in that you have here a red horſe following a white, as afterward a black one going out after this red, we may obſerve, <hi>That the Church continues not long
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:162107:6"/>in any condition, but is ſubject to variety of changes;</hi> That ſhe may not ſurfeit on any adminiſtration, that ſhe may have opportunity to exerciſe every grace, and learne to beare every condition. Strange not then at changes, but rather ſtill expect viciſſitudes of peace and trouble, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity and adverſity; that in the one you may not be proud for feare of a fall, and that in the other you may be kept from fainting, by hope of raiſing, for changes are not long away.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, in that power was given him to take away peace, without which he could do nothing, obſerve, <hi>That Peace never is nor can be taken away without ſpeciall commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, In that a great ſword was given to the Rider who was to do theſe feats, we may obſerve, <hi>That when God intends any worke he uſually raiſeth up meanes anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, And againe, <hi>All the power that men have to act or accompliſh deſignes, they are furniſhed with it by the providence of God:</hi> it is he that endues with power to hurt or help, but on none of theſe ſhall I inſiſt, but on two others; the one gathered from the thing repreſented, an <hi>Horſe,</hi> another from that part of his worke, that by <hi>taking away peace from the earth,</hi> he ſhould ingage men in <hi>mutuall ſlaughter.</hi> Firſt, from that God revealing what judgement he would bring on the world for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Goſpell doth typifie this; by <hi>a red horſe</hi> we learne,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. The firſt Doctrine handled.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the judgements that are deſigned of God against any people, will (when Gods time is come) ruſh in upon them ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, and irreſiſtably, notwithstanding all the oppoſition that can be made.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:162107:7"/>
               <p>The frequent uſe of this type by the holy Ghoſt may be a full proofe of this point. So <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 106.29. <hi>Thus they provoked him to anger with their inventions, and the plague broke in upon them,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> The plague made an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption upon them like the waters upon a ſe a-banke, or a troupe of Horſe upon a band of Foot. So on <hi>Senacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib,</hi> when the Angell of the Lord went forth <hi>and ſmote in one night an hundred foureſcore and five thouſand. Iſa.</hi> 38.36. So on <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> when God with an high hand brought out his people out of <hi>Aegypt that very day of his deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Exod.</hi> 12.14. notwithſtanding the hardneſſe of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi> heart, and the might of his hand; <hi>for in what they dealt proudly, God was above them. Exod.</hi> 18.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rea. </seg>
                  </label> Further to convince this, this one reaſon may be ſufficient, becauſe the judgements that are deſigned by God are alſo effected by him; he hath an oare in the boate, an hand in the execution, and he is an Agent of that power that he can neither be reſiſted, nor delayed, longer then he pleaſeth, for he can worke immediately, and he that can worke without meanes, there is no poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of reſiſting or delaying him: humane reſiſtance is by oppoſing meanes to meanes, no reſiſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> then againſt an immediate hand, nor delay neither; for he that needs no meanes, whoſe willing is effecting, he is ready to worke every moment, and in what moment he will can make the plague begin: thus dealt he with <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 25.38. <hi>The Lord ſmote Nabal that he dyed.</hi> So with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, while the word was in his mouth,</hi> though he were the only Potentate on earth, <hi>the word was ſpoken from heaven, and the ſame houre the deſigne was exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted: Dan.</hi> 4.31, 33.</p>
               <p>Secondly, God can worke by <hi>Angels</hi> that come upon us inviſibly, and with greater might then we have to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:162107:7"/>oppoſe; It is true in a ſpirituall ſence, we may reſiſt the <hi>devill</hi> a curſed ſpirit, ſo as he will be put to flight. <hi>Iames</hi> 4.7. But in a corporall way if God let them looſe, we can neither make reſiſtance againſt good or evill <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> What way or meanes was there for that huge hoſt of <hi>Senacharib</hi> to make reſiſtance againſt the <hi>Angell</hi> that ſlew them? what are <hi>Swords,</hi> or <hi>Guns,</hi> or <hi>Armour of proof,</hi> to a <hi>ſpirit</hi> that cannot be annoyed by the one, but can come within the other, and deſtroy?</p>
               <p n="3">3. He can worke by the <hi>heavens</hi> to make them as <hi>braſſe,</hi> that the earth may become as <hi>Iron,</hi> or open the windows of heaven to corrupt the creatures on the ground, and what reſiſtance then? Who can bind the moiſt influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the <hi>Pleyades?</hi> &amp;c. ſee <hi>Iob</hi> 38.31. <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.22.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If he will worke by meanes that are in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture reſiſtable, yet he can cloath them with ſuch power, and put ſuch ſpirits into them, that all ſhall bow before them, as he did firſt raiſe up <hi>Nebuchadnezzar and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then him, Ezek.</hi> 30.24, 25. and after him <hi>Cyrus, Iſa.</hi> 45.1, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If he will uſe weake meanes he can make them beare downe the ſtrongeſt reſiſtance; He can make <hi>a barly cake overthrow a Tent, and</hi> Gideon, <hi>and</hi> 300. <hi>with lamps and trumpets, diſcomfit an Army, Iudg.</hi> 7. And de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver a <hi>great Army into the hands of a ſmall company of men,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.24. <hi>that ſo they may execute his judgements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. If there be rubs in the way, and thoſe as great in mans eye, and as immoveable as mountaines, yet God can, and will make them plaines, <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.7. God rules in and over all thoſe that ſhould make oppoſition; They live move and have their being in him, and he can take them away; he can ſtrike them with ſickneſſe, as he did that politique <hi>Nephew</hi> of the <hi>Popes, Caeſar Borgias,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:162107:8"/>and fruſtrate their ſtrongeſt contrivances:
<note place="margin">* <hi>Mihi dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it</hi> (ſaith <hi>Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell) ſe ad omnem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quem a patris morte fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taret, longe in poſterum proſpexiſſe, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſe: illud uaum dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat ſe praeteriiſſe, quod ſcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet nanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putarat ſub ejus morte, ſibi etiam cum morte eſſe conſligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi> Nich. Mach. prin. Cap. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Who would have thought</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that I ſhould have been ſicke when my father dyed.</hi> He can ſtrike them with terrour that their hearts ſhall melt, and their hands be weake, as thoſe Nations mightier than Iſrael, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 5.1. He can befoole them, and make them haſten that ruine which they would avoyd, by that meanes which they thinke to avoid it; Thus did he <hi>Abſalom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.14. yea, he can turne their owne force upon themſelves (as now upon <hi>England)</hi> if he purpoſe to make them miſerable, See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.14, 15. In a word, God hath not only ſuch wiſdome and power over all, that none is able to reſiſt, but he hath that rule in all, that none ſhall have a will to reſiſt what he deſignes ſhall come to paſſe further than he orders the reſiſtance to be made. Now put all theſe together, and may we not well conclude that his judgments are fitly repreſented as ſpeedy, and irreſiſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? This may be improved three waies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. The Uſes of the Point.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, this may be for the <hi>juſt terrour and uſefull awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of all ſuch as careleſly ruſh into ſin, to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves lyable to Gods judgements; ſee what their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, how quickly and ſurely their judgements will come when God appoints. Gods judgements come on horſebacke, and ſo make ſpeed, and are unavoidable. <hi>If I whet my glittering ſword</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and mine hand take hold of judgement, I will render vengeance to mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, &amp;c. Deut.</hi> 32.41, 42. It is true, God is long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and not quick in deſigning judgments, and this men uſually abuſe, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Becauſe ſentence is not executed ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, the hearts of the ſons of men are ſet in them to do evill;</hi> but when God once deſigns judgements, then they ſleepe not, then he ſends out his horſemen, whoſe names may
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162107:8"/>be <hi>Maher-ſhalal-haſh-bas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 8.1.</note> for they will ſpeedily do their worke, and ſpoile us of our comforts; And ſhould wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sinners then be ſecure? Is not he afraid that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the diſpleaſure of one that hath a great Army, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of horſe, that can come on him ſuddenly, and trample him down? Such is the caſe of men with God, that live in waies of provocation; <hi>Oh conſider this ye that forget God,</hi> and provoke him to indignation with Oaths, Blaſphemies, Whoredomes, Drunkeneſſe, Oppreſſion, Profaneneſſe, &amp;c. How can you be ſecure, and have to deale with ſuch a God? Or put far from you the evill day, when Gods judgements come one horſebacke? Therefore learne to feare.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, This may be a <hi>warning to all to take heed of provoking God to anger, who appoints his judgements to come in ſuch a manner that we can neither avoid them, nor delay them;</hi> Why ſhould we ſin againſt ſuch an one? Is not that to ſin againſt our owne peace and weale? <hi>Ier.</hi> 7.19. <hi>A prudent man foreſeeth the evill and hideth himſelfe, fooles paſſe on and are puniſhed, Prov.</hi> 22.3. There is a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of <hi>faith,</hi> as well as of <hi>Sagacity;</hi> and may not faith in theſe Types ſee the danger that is in ſin, that maketh liable to ſwift, and unavoydable judgements, that we may hide our ſelves by withdrawing from ſin? Why hath God revealed this manner of his judgements breaking in upon us, but for our warning? And what will this warning do but make inexcuſable if not made uſe of? God hath <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> mixt with his <hi>Greatneſſe.</hi> He will not <hi>oppreſſe</hi> us when <hi>innocent;</hi> Nor <hi>reject</hi> us when <hi>ſupplyant:</hi> But if we go on <hi>ſtubborne</hi> in ſin theſe will make us <hi>inexcuſable,</hi> and more <hi>pitileſly miſerable;</hi> be wiſe now therefore and depart from evill.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, <hi>This may yeeld wholeſome counſell to thoſe that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162107:9"/>have already ſinned.</hi> It is their beſt way to make their peace, and that ſpeedily: this is the counſell of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.25. <hi>Agree with thine adverſary quickly,</hi> &amp;c. that is, with God whom thou haſt made an adverſary by thy ſin; you cannot meet him with ten thouſand, nor ten thouſand times ten thouſand; he can ſend out an Angell that can deſtroy in a night. Therefore agree and that quickly leſt it be too late, for his judgements come on horſebacke, and a little delay may make it to late. God may forbeare, to wait for amendment, becauſe he is long-ſuffering, and would have men come to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but when the time of patience is out, his Agents horſe and away; therefore deferre not making thy peace with God. Yea, <hi>this may further informe us of the way to ſecure our ſelves from the wrath of God,</hi> not by <hi>force,</hi> but <hi>ſubmiſsion;</hi> his judgements come on horſebacke fiercely, and irreſiſtably, no ſafety therefore in <hi>oppoſition</hi> but in <hi>ſubmiſsion; There is no Wiſdome, Counſell, nor Strength againſt God.</hi> There hath been diſpute by ſome, <hi>whether his grace were reſiſtable,</hi> but none have been ſo hardy as to diſpute <hi>the reſiſtability of his power;</hi> yet there is a way to overcome God, but it is not the vvay of the <hi>Gyants,</hi> but of <hi>Iacob;</hi> it is not by <hi>oppoſition,</hi> but <hi>ſubmiſsion,</hi> by <hi>Prayers and teares of repentance, Hoſ.</hi> 12.4. You cannot overcome the <hi>hands</hi> of <hi>God</hi> by <hi>might,</hi> but you may overcome the <hi>heart</hi> of <hi>God</hi> by <hi>melting;</hi> if you be froward like briers and thornes you will find God as fire to burne; but if you fall downe and lay hold on him to make peace, you ſhall find peace with him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.4, 5. Humble therefore, and ſubmit to God to make your peace, and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as the judgements of God are <hi>irreſiſtable,</hi> ſo are they many times <hi>unſufferable</hi> and <hi>deſtructive,</hi> as you ſee it followes, <hi>Commiſsion was given to this Rider to take away
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:162107:9"/>peace from the earth, and that they ſhould kill one another.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect. 6.</hi> The ſecond Doctrine handled.</head>
               <p>That <hi>they ſhould kill one another,</hi> this is the effect of the loſſe of peace; whence,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>When Peace is taken away, mutuall ſlaughter followes.</hi> 
               </p>
               <p>You may read this in the Story of the Bible. <hi>Iudges</hi> 20.21, 25, 35, 48. When peace was interrupted in <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> by the wickedneſſe of the men of <hi>Gibeah,</hi> and the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe of the <hi>Benjamites</hi> to protect them, there were ſlaughtered in a few daies <hi>twenty and two thouſand,</hi> ver. 21. and <hi>eighteen thouſand,</hi> ver. 25. and <hi>twenty and five thouſand men,</hi> ver. 35. beſides, <hi>all the men, women, and children of</hi> Benjamin <hi>that went not forth to war,</hi> ver. 48. So upon a breach between <hi>Pekah</hi> the Son of <hi>Remaliah,</hi> and <hi>Ahaz</hi> King of <hi>Iudah, Pekah</hi> ſlew in <hi>Iuda</hi> an hundred and twenty thouſand in one day which were all valiant men, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.6. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.29. upon a quarrell betweene <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> the children of Iſrael <hi>ſlew an hundred thouſand foot-men in one day;</hi> but above all, upon a cir ill breach between <hi>Abiah</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and <hi>Iereboam</hi> King of Iſrael <hi>there fell downe ſlaine of Iſrael five hundred thouſand choſen men.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.17. But we read this in our own Hiſtories too, for in that one quarrell, when peace was taken from <hi>England</hi> by the <hi>depoſition</hi> (or rather forced <hi>reſignation)</hi> of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, what ſlaughter folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of one another? Our <hi>Historians reckon</hi> 12. <hi>ſet battles fought, foureſcore Princes of the Bloud ſlain, and above foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore thouſand of all degrees, by Engliſhmen in our owne Kingdome, beſides thoſe that fell in</hi> France <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>by this occaſion.</hi> But what need we go to Story for proofe? Since peace hath been taken from <hi>England</hi> in our daies, what ſuperabundant ſlaughters of one another have wee ſeen or heard of?</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:162107:10"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Peace is taken away by war, <hi>and in war it is mens worke to kill one another;</hi> as every particular trade hath its particular worke, ſo the particular worke of Souldiers is to kill others, and he is the moſt famous in that Profeſſion that is moſt dexterous in ſlaughter. It is counted but a <hi>ſport in war to kill one another;</hi> 2 Sam. 2.14, 15, 16. <hi>And</hi> Abner <hi>ſaid to</hi> Joab, <hi>let the young men now ariſe and play before us; and</hi> Joab <hi>ſaid, let them ariſe; Then there aroſe and went over by number twelve of</hi> Benjamin <hi>which pertained to</hi> Iſhboſheth <hi>the Son of</hi> Saul, <hi>and twelve of the Servants of</hi> David. <hi>And they caught every one his fellow by the head, and thruſt his ſword in his fellowes ſide, ſo they fell downe together.</hi> This is the ſport of War; And hence it may be the phraſe is borrowed of having the great or ſmall ſhot play upon oppoſites to ſlaughter them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>In war there are prepared ſlaughtering inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> and as inſtruments are more deſtructive, ſo are they more ſet by, <hi>Swords, Pole-axes, Speares, Piſtols, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, Muskets, Murthering-pieces, Canons, Mortar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces, Granadoes,</hi> and what not that is deſtructive; <hi>Eze.</hi> 9.1, 2. There ſee this in a Type, <hi>cauſe them that have the charge over the City to draw neere, even every man with his deſtroying weapon in his hand;</hi> And where ſuch inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are on both ſides ſubſervient to intentions of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, what mutuall ſlaughter is like to follow?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>In times of War men of fierce natures and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions are moſt imployed, and custome is a ſecond nature.</hi> Men count it wiſdome in all deſignes to chuſe Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments fit to execute them. Now War being to deſtroy, thoſe of rougheſt natures, that will not relent at cries and bloud, are fitteſt timber for the harſh worke of ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; as <hi>Ex quo libet ligno non fit Mercurius, So nor</hi> Mars, <hi>all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:162107:10"/>tempers are not fit to make Souldiers of;</hi> Even God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe when he would have execution done on <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſtirred up the <hi>Medes</hi> againſt them, <hi>a flinty people, that would not be withheld from ſlaughter by price, nor pitty,</hi> Iſa. 13.17, 18. <hi>Where Nature is wanting, Custome makes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> therefore no Souldier to the old Souldier, not only becauſe experience makes him prudent and hardy, but hardned in heart too, that he makes light of the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of friend or foe; <hi>What is cuſtomary affects little.</hi> Nay, generally thoſe that are made uſe of in War are ſuch as are looſe and deboiſt, that have put off humanity in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of morality, and civility, and ſo cannot have much pitty, for men given up to vile affections become with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out naturall affection, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.26, 31. Now when ſuch men have the uſe of ſuch weapons, and that of purpoſe to deſtroy, what ſlaughter is like to follow?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>In time of War men have advantage by killing, which in times of Peace doth indammage them.</hi> In War killing is their <hi>ſafety;</hi> A man ſaves his owne, by taking away the life of others that ſeeke his ruine: but in Peace he that takes away the life of another (unleſſe in judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) forfeits his own. In Peace men by killing forfeit their owne goods, but in War they take the ſpoile of thoſe whom they have ſlaine. In War they have honour by killing, but in Peace a ſtaine and blot. And ſo it is moſt plaine, where Peace is taken away men do and will kill one another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> We may improve this holy truth, firſt for <hi>Information, to evidence unto us what an heavy judgement War is in a Nation, eſpecially a Civill War,</hi> becauſe in it men kill one another. The heavineſſe of the judgement may hence appeare in two reſpects: in <hi>reſpect of the guilt of it,</hi> and <hi>the burthen of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:162107:11"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>In reſpect of the guilt of it;</hi> War gives Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſlaughter, and man-killing is a grievous ſin; <hi>Bloud is crying, Gen.</hi> 4.10. God was irreconcileable for this, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 24.4. It is true that there is a juſt <hi>War,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to <hi>kill</hi> is not to <hi>murther,</hi> but to do <hi>execution;</hi> as in <hi>Iehues</hi> War upon the houſe of <hi>Ahab</hi> at Gods appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and the Wars of <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> which were the <hi>Lords Battels;</hi> yet in ſuch caſes a lawfull Act may be done unlawfully, as in that of <hi>Iehu,</hi> whence that threatning, <hi>Heſ.</hi> 1.4. <hi>I will viſit the bloud of</hi> Ieſreel <hi>upon the houſe of</hi> Jehu. It is an hard and rare thing to do exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution in War without corrupt aimes which will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract guilt: But further in a <hi>Civill War</hi> there muſt needs be injuſtice on one ſide, and ſo innocent bloud muſt needs be ſhed; Nay, ſometimes both ſides may be faulty, in not doing what <hi>is poſsible, and as much as in them lies to have peace,</hi> which is their duty, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.18. which charge of the Apoſtle being given of private peace, where the breach is not attended with ſo ſad a conſequence as bloud, muſt needs be more ingaging in publique peace to prevent War, which ſets men on kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling one another; and where both ſides are guilty, how is a Land defiled? Beſides, in a Civill War there is not only <hi>homicide,</hi> but <hi>parricide</hi> and <hi>fratricide;</hi> Sometimes the <hi>Father</hi> kils the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Son</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> and one <hi>brother</hi> another, which propinquity makes more hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous; So this makes a Civill War grievous, becauſe it multiplies that mighty ſin of Bloud; while other croſſes make <hi>white and refine, Dan.</hi> 11.35. This of a Civill War doth <hi>defile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>War is agrievous judgement in regard of the burthen of it,</hi> which hence appeares, becauſe it brings ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with it. Thoſe judgements are heavieſt that are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:162107:11"/>moſt deſtructive to thoſe on whom they light, and that War is, for it brings ſlaughter; It weakens and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours a Nation, for what folly is it for a Nation to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it ſelfe? And whom doth War deſtroy? Doth it make any diſtinction, unleſſe in ſparing thoſe that are leaſt conſiderable? <hi>But the Captaine of the guard left of the poore of the people,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 25.12. The Sword makes no diſtinction of good or bad, Prince or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour; <hi>the Sword devours one as well as another,</hi> ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.25. <hi>The precious Sons of Sion comparable to fine gold, how are they eſteemed as earthen pitchers, to wit, in the prevailing of VVar, Lam.</hi> 4.2. A <hi>Bullet</hi> will kill a <hi>Prince</hi> as ſoon as a <hi>Peaſant:</hi> Nay, uſually in War thoſe are moſt attempted that are greateſt, as the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable oppoſites, the Captaines and Commanders are moſt aymed at, and there is moſt glorying in the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſuch, as moſt uſefull ſervice; when <hi>Ioab</hi> had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatcht <hi>Abſalom,</hi> he ſounded a retreat, and let the reſt eſcape. Now in a Civill War the publique weale loſeth on both ſides, the Land is wounded and dyes in both Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and is deprived of ſome of thoſe that are her ſtrength, beauty, and glory; <hi>The mighty man, and the man of VVar, the Iudge, and the Prophet, and the Prudent, and the Ancient, the Captaine of fifty, and the Honourable,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.2, 3. Oh then how proper and ſignificant is that expreſſion of the Prophet? <hi>Ier.</hi> 16.5. <hi>I have taken away my peace from my people, even my mercy and loving kindneſſe.</hi> When peace goes, ſlaughter comes, God doth not ſpare or pitty; and ſo mercy and loving kindneſſe goes when peace goes. How ſhould we then carry our ſelves under ſuch a ſtroke as this? Should we not walke as they uſe the Phraſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14. mournfully before the Lord of Hoaſts, walke in black, neglecting ornaments and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:162107:12"/>jollity? ſhould we not carry our ſelves as <hi>filii ſub ira,</hi> as Children under their Fathers diſpleaſure, ſad and reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, ſo long as ſuch a cloud of indignation hangs over us? Is not this the day wherein God cals for <hi>faſting and ſackcloath?</hi> And ſhall we now brave it? Shall we now be as joviall as ever? <hi>A Sword is ſharpened to make ſore ſlaughter, it is furbiſhed that it may glitter, and ſhall we now make m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rth? Ezek.</hi> 21.16. Certainly, if we humble not under ſuch an hand, it is a ſigne of blinded minds and hardened hearts to uſher in deſolation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, for <hi>reprehenſion of thoſe that kindle the fire of VVar in a Nation, or blow it up, or adde fewell to it, or hinder, or at leaſt further not the extinguiſhing of it, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if it be a Civill VVar:</hi> VVar brings ſlaughter, which they are acceſſary to that any way promote it, or hinder it not; <hi>Quod eſt cauſa cauſae eſt cauſa cauſa cauſati.</hi> Now men may further and be acceſſary to VVar morally, or Phyſically.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Morally:</hi> So ſuch as are guilty of thoſe ſins that make God an enemy, and provoke him to grant out a Commiſſion (as here) for the taking away of peace. Sin is the firſt moving cauſe of VVar: The Maſter wheele that ſets all other on worke, and tampering with other things are uſually fruſtrate till this be rectified; And that is the apparant reaſon why ſo many attempts for accommodation among us have been uſeleſſe; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever were the next cauſe, ſin unreformed was the remote and meritorious cauſe; <hi>VVhat peace</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iehu</hi> to <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram) ſo long as the whoredomes of thy mother</hi> Jezabell, <hi>and her witchcrafts are ſo many?</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9.22. And therefore the VVars that have waſted the people of God have been uſually charged on their ſins; that oppreſſion by <hi>Iabin, Iudges</hi> 4. is charged on their Idolatry; <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.8. <hi>They
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:162107:12"/>choſe new Gods, then was VVar in their Gates,</hi> &amp;c. That Civill VVar made by <hi>Abſalom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. was but the ſcourge of <hi>Davids</hi> ſcandall occaſioning Blaſphemy, as the threatning ſhewes, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.11. with 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.22. Thoſe Adverſaries that moleſted <hi>Salomons</hi> peace, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.14, 23. and <hi>Shiſhakes</hi> drawing the ſword upon <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> were but the puniſhment of their Apoſtacy, as was that alſo by the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> on <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. &amp; 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 24.24. VVhy was the latter end of <hi>Aſaes</hi> raign moleſted with VVars, but for his confiding in man, and not reſting on God? 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 16.7, 9. VVhy were the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> let in on the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> but for their hypocriſie, and formality? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.6, 7. VVhy was that great deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion brought upon Iſrael by the <hi>Babylonians</hi> but for their ſins, chiefly for that of Oppreſſion and Bloud? <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.12, 13. <hi>The Kings of the earth, and all the Inhabitants of the world would not have thought that the adverſary and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhould have entered into the Gates of</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>For the ſins of her Prophets, and the iniquities of her Prieſts that have ſhed the bloud of the juſt in the midſt of her.</hi> And what was the cauſe of this <hi>red Horſe</hi> following the <hi>white,</hi> but the contempt of the Goſpell, and perſecution of it by the heathen Emperours, and their Agents, and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers? And therefore thoſe that are guilty of theſe and the like ſins, we may ſay of them as <hi>Ieremiah</hi> to <hi>Zedeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> in caſe he followed not his counſell, <hi>Ier.</hi> 38.23. <hi>And thou ſhalt cauſe this City to be burnt with fire;</hi> So they by their ſins, and impenitency have miniſtred fuell to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin and prolong our civill flame which will be no ſmall aggravation of their ſin, that this might awaken the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in <hi>Sion,</hi> and help to breake them for, and from their ſins, that have ſuch an influence on this deſolating ſtroake on their deare Country, and Brethren.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:162107:13"/>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Phyſically, as proper efficients or nouriſhing cauſes of it; So ſome that count it their trade, their harveſt,</hi> and therefore now others have begun it they will keep it up; They know not how to live or maintaine their humour and luſts without it. <hi>Others, that in another kind advance their intereſt by it;</hi> they know how to <hi>warme</hi> themſelves by that fire which <hi>burnes</hi> others: They have profitable offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, can command, and rule, keep off accounts, &amp;c. <hi>Some well affected to peace in the generall, yet thinke this is not a fit time to endeavour peace by Treaty,</hi> till all oppoſite force be laid, whoſe objection we ſhall anſwer anon, what ever the cauſe be that make men averſe to Treaty, and ſo willing to prolong Civill VVar it wants not guilt: though the worſe the cauſe the worſe is the effect that flowes from it. Theſe will be acceſſar, to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of men, and judged cruell on whom the thought of deſtruction of their brethren hath no more working. Can any tell on which ſide the ſlaughter will moſt fall? On which ſide ſoever it fall, are not the ſlaine the ſlaine of the daughter of our people? And you know what a corraſive that was to <hi>Ieremiahs</hi> heart when the people of his time were as wicked as thoſe of our time be: <hi>O that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe day and night for the ſlaine of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of my people, Ier.</hi> 9.1. Surely ſuch a temper would never have produced an impediment to the cloſing of our breach by Treaty; I may therefore leave a blacke note on thoſe that retard the reſtoring of Peace, though with ſome diſtinction of bad or worſe, accordingly as there is weakeneſſe or pravity in the cauſe from which it flowes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, And laſt may be <hi>to quicken us all to ſtudy the recovery of peace,</hi> becauſe without peace nothing is ſeen,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:162107:13"/>or can be expected but mutuall ſlaughter, and this ſlaughter will not want bitterneſſe, nor guilt, while we move not every ſtone for a well grounded peace: All are for peace, but ſome would have it by the Sword; their word is <hi>Enſe pacem petimus</hi> — Others would have it by Treaty. Now here is an argument to encline to ſeeke Peace by Treaty, becauſe till Peace is recovered men will kill one another: And to this we may adde theſe following conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive </seg>1</label> 1. <hi>We have had experience of conqueſt on one ſide alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and have found</hi> that the Sword prevailing on one ſide will not make laſting Peace, neither is this appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in moderne experience only, but in ancient alſo. It was neither the vanquiſhing of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, or <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth: No nor the <hi>death</hi> of either that did, or could ſettle this Kingdome in a firme Peace, nor any thing elſe, but an <hi>accommodation</hi> in the union of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, Heire of the Houſe of <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> matching with the <hi>Daughter</hi> and <hi>Heyreſſe</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>York.</hi> This was the only cure under God of our longeſt Civill VVars: it may be the Sword on the other ſide may make Peace, but with danger of that ſlavery, that (I beleeve) you are ſufficiently apprehenſive of; but on the other part, the Sword is not like to make a ſetled Peace without Treaty, and Accomodation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Conſider our War is a Civill War,</hi> wherein the Land bleeds, and is weakened on both ſides, and loſeth thoſe many times that may ſtand her in ſtead both in Peace, and Forraign VVars; which conſideration would be the more weighty if we would remember that witty Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Duke of <hi>Rohan, England is a great Animall, that cannot dye unleſſe it kill it ſelfe;</hi> being ſo warned, ſhall we hold up the only courſe for ſelfe deſtruction?</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:162107:14"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Conſider the dependance that one Church hath upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> that in the ſtrength, or weakeneſſe of one, all other are weakened, or ſtrengthened: So that in <hi>Englands</hi> wounds all Proteſtant Churches ſuffer, and will eaſilier be a prey to any of the Limbes of Antichriſt; and what a ſad thing were it that <hi>England,</hi> that hath been a refuge to Proteſtants, ſhould now occaſion their weakening.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Conſider the little benefit that will accrew by bloudſhed now,</hi> (if it want guilt) In ſome waies and ſufferings the loſſe of bloud may yeeld ſweet fruit, and we may expect increaſe by it; <hi>Sanguinis Martyrum, ſemen Eccleſiae: Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs Bloud, is the Churches Seed.</hi> So in our <hi>Marian</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, I am confident God hath bleſſed the Land with more faithfull Preachers and Profeſſors, by the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our <hi>Martyrs</hi> bloud <hi>(who being dead yet ſpeake)</hi> then their labours would have procured had they lived out that ordinary time, that in reaſon and nature they might; but no ſuch crop can be expected from the bloud now ſhed.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The hazzard that muſt be run:</hi> who knowes where victory will light: and if it light on the ſide of thoſe that are moſt averſe to Peace by Treaty, in what caſe will that Liberty, and Religion, &amp;c. be, that they moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? It is not good to hazzard all, when we may by Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty obtaine that which we would and might heretofore have reſted contented with, and thankfull for.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>And what muſt become of poore</hi> Ireland? Muſt we ſtill complaine to God that it is <hi>called an out caſt that no man ſeeketh after;</hi> and yet not take courſes that may haſten her reliefe? which ſure is likelier to be haſtened by our cloſure by Treaty, than expecting an end by the Sword.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>And me thinkes it ſhould ſomewhat move moderate
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:162107:14"/>ſpirits to conſider who they have been that have been moſt averſe to an end by Treaty.</hi> VVere not <hi>Papiſts</hi> uſed to cry out on the one hand that they were undone when hopes of Accommodation appeared, while the moſt <hi>Hereticall Sectaries</hi> looked blacke on the other hand? Are they not the moſt dangerous on both ſides, that would have no peace with a King, or with a Parliament? Sure then all that feare the dangers of extreames ſhould cloſe in their deſires, and endeavours for Peace by ſuch a Treaty as might preſerve both King and Parliament, with the Royalties of the one, and the Priviledges of the other.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Nor ſhould that be of leaſt weight with us that is here hinted in the Text: The Rider</hi> (as our <hi>Gyffard</hi> ſaith) <hi>on this red horſe is the Devill,</hi> his worke it is to take Peace from the earth, that men might kill one another; ſo that they that lay any Remora in the way of Peace, they are but the devils Agents, who doth either blow up their corruption as in thoſe Perſecutors who played the devill, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Some of you ſhall Sathan caſt into priſon,</hi> not immediately, but by his Agents, or elſe he doth abuſe their ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as ſometimes he did <hi>Peters</hi> to Chriſt, when he thus rebuked him, <hi>get thee behind me Sathan, Mat.</hi> 16.23. But there is an Objection or two that needs ſolution.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>Some may thinke that if we have Peace with Treaty, we ſhall not have all truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>1</label> It is true, that <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Holineſſe</hi> are more precious than <hi>Peace,</hi> and we muſt not let go either for outward Peace, for that were to part with <hi>God</hi> for <hi>man: Heaven</hi> for <hi>earth: Inward</hi> for <hi>outward Peace;</hi> which were a ſinfull and fooliſh change; but yet,</p>
               <p>Firſt, I ſay, <hi>by Treaty we may have publiquely all the Peace that it is lawfull for us to fight for,</hi> which we have proteſted to maintaine; that is, all that is contained in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:162107:15"/>the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I ſay, <hi>If any errour be left we ſhall not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to it,</hi> having within our Spheare profeſt againſt it, and endeavoured the eradication of it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>We may for our owne particular hold all truth and purity,</hi> that is a Legacy that Chriſt hath purchaſed for us that none can take away: They may trouble and moleſt us for it, but cannot without our owne conſent diſpoyle us of it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>We may have publiquely more truth ſetled by Treaty than we are like to have by Victory on either ſide;</hi> we have had experience on the one ſide already; And I beleeve few of you doubt of my Aſſertion, if Victory ſhould fall on the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>But ſome may thinke that this is not a fit time to Treate, till the Forces up againſt the Parliament be reduced, but then it will be ſeaſonable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> To omit other things that might be anſwered to this Objection, I anſwer briefly; <hi>Though the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that be now raiſed againſt the Parliament make it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what inconvenient to Treat in ſome reſpects, yet in ſome other it makes it more neceſſary.</hi> A Treaty, I confeſſe, is not ſo honourable when in any degree enforced, and it is convenient that it ſhould be done with the greateſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility and freedome; but that opportunity being loſt, now the Force that is up doth neceſſitate it, if we will prevent grievous and hazzardous ſlaughter. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for my part, I cannot but wonder that any wiſe men, though never ſo oppoſite to <hi>conjunction</hi> with other Forces riſen, ſhould not think them a juſt <hi>occaſion</hi> though not to <hi>precipitate,</hi> yet to <hi>haſten</hi> a Treaty, ſeeing elſe ſo great ſlaughter is like to be, becauſe now, as it followes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:162107:15"/>in the Text there is given to them a great Sword, that may ſhed much precious bloud.</p>
               <p>But ſomething is requiſite in us to promote Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides endeavouring Treaty, for we muſt ſtudy every one of us <hi>to be fit for the returne of Peace;</hi> God gives it, and God takes it away, and God waites to be gratious, giving mercies to his people when they are fit for them. Now we are fit for Peace, firſt, <hi>when we rightly prize it,</hi> which want of it ſhould, and may teach us: for <hi>Bona carendo, &amp;c. Good things are best knowne in their value by our wanting them;</hi> when we prize a bleſſing we will be thankefull for it. Secondly, <hi>when we are fitted to improve it,</hi> when we are broken for, and healed of all our abuſes of it: when we can looke upon it as a gracious opportunity to do more good, and reſolve by way of thankfulneſſe ſo to improve it. Thirdly, <hi>when God hath done his whole good worke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us by War, Iſa.</hi> 10.7, 12. when we are refined, humbled, and brought to repent of all thoſe ſins which have brought the judgement of War upon us, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>We muſt ſtudy to make our peace with God;</hi> his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie with us is the root of all Controverſies among our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>We muſt not only petition men but God,</hi> and that with ſuch earneſtneſſe, ſincerity, and importunity, as ſuch a mercy ſhould be ſought, and then God will returne our peace as a river; which the Lord vouchſafe.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Soli Deo gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:162107:16"/>
            <head>An Appendix holding forth the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Preaching, and the cauſe of publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, this plaine Sermon.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou mayeſt underſtand that on <hi>Friday</hi> in the afternoone, <hi>Iuly</hi> 14. an earneſt ſuit was moved to me from Dr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Burgeſſe,</hi> to ſupply Dr. <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> place at <hi>Pauls</hi> the Lords day following, and withall an offer made of ſufficient ſupply for my charge that afternoone. This ſute being ſo preſt, &amp; being ſo ſmall, for but the exchange of a Sermon, and by ſuch Perſons, I could not be ſo uncivill as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.24. <hi>He that hath friends muſt ſhew himſelfe friendly.</hi> The next day when I was to make my prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I fell into a diſtemper with a cold affecting one ſide of my head and face, which unfitting me in a great degree for ſtudy, I was forced to make uſe of old ſtore; And caſting in my thoughts what ſubject to pitch upon, at length I determined on this Subject, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.4. For though I have alwaies thought it baſeneſſe below a Chriſtian to ſerve the times, yet I have thought it wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome requiſite in a Miniſter to ſute the times with a fit Subject; yea, part of that prudence whereby he is to ſhew himſelfe a workman that needs not to be aſhamed, dividing the word of Truth aright. Now at that time the City was intent upon Peace to be procured by Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which worke, though generally well accepted, yet
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:162107:16"/>finding ſome diſcouragement, I thought by the miſchiefe of War to take occaſion to incourage them in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſute of Peace in that way that might ſooneſt end, and beſt prevent the ſad conſequences of our unnaturall war; being thus called to this Pulpit, and inclined to this Subject, I preacht this Sermon in a great and very at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive Auditory, and then thought that worke had been at an end. But contrary to mine expectation, not long after I heard of a rumour ſpread, not in the City only, but even in the Country, of a notorious malignant Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preacht by me at <hi>Pauls;</hi> And this brought to me by, and from, perſons not to be contemned. This, I confeſſe, moved me, for true Malignancy is of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and even reputed Malignancy of that evill conſequence, that as <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith of <hi>Hereſie, it is an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation that a man ſhould not be patient under;</hi> patient in regard of murmuring, fretting, revenging, we ſhould be under all croſſes: but patient in regard of neglecting juſt and vigorous vindication we ſhould not be in ſuch calumnies as this of Malignancy: For a Malignant notes out ſuch an one, as hath evill will at, and doth ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to hinder the publique weale of Church or State. I know the tearme is uſually caſt by men in all times of difference on thoſe that ſide not with any Party in thoſe waies that they deeme for publique weale, though in themſelves never ſo deſtructive. So <hi>Eliah</hi> was counted a Malignant by <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.17. And <hi>Ieremy</hi> too in his time for perſwading ſubmiſſion to the King of <hi>Babylon, as weakening the hands of the men of War,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ier.</hi> 38.4. But true Malignity is enmity to weale pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, and by that imputation men intend to blaſt all thoſe that dance not after their Pipe. And he that is guilty of ſuch Malignity is a peſt or viper in that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:162107:17"/>Church or State which he malignes. Yet a while I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented my ſelfe with <hi>that brazen wall of a good conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Murus ahe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus eſto, nil conſcire ſibi.</note> as thinking it ſufficient defence againſt thoſe arrowes of the tongue; but they encreaſing, and conſidering that obſervation of the wiſe Hiſtorian, <hi>Periculoſum eſt ſolâ in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentiâ vivere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Livy.</note> In diſtempered times eſpecially <hi>it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to have no other guard but innocency;</hi> I thought ſome neceſſity layd upon me to vindicate my reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from ſuch a crime: And reſolving upon defence, I knew no better, nor no other than a naked repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Sermon to the eyes of all, that was ſo ſeverally reliſht by the eares in hearing. And to this I was the eaſilier induced, becauſe, at the earneſt deſires of ſome that approved it, I had engaged my ſelfe to draw out a faire copy of it. I remember a Story of <hi>Sophocles. Who being accuſed by his Sons for dotage, that by the opinion of the Iudges they might enter on his Eſtate; in this hazzard, having in his hands the Comedy</hi> Oedipus Colonaeus <hi>which he had laſt compoſed, is ſaid to have recited that to the Iudges, and demanded of them whether they thought that thoſe were the verſes of a doter;</hi> Whereupon <hi>Sententiis judicium li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beratus eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicero de ſenectute.</note> 
               <hi>The Iudges freed him from the accuſation:</hi> In like manner my Sermon being accuſed for Malignancy, I knew no better way of defence than a publication of it as neere as I could verbatim (eſpecially in Points whereat exceptions were taken) with this appeale to the conſcience of the Reader, <hi>Num verba haec maligni vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur,</hi> whether theſe ſeem to be the words of a Malignant. Is it Malignancy to charge ſin as the greateſt breaker of our peace, and ſinners as the greateſt troublers of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> To preſſe them by repentance to deliver <hi>England</hi> out of the hand of the Lord? Is it Malignancy to ſet out the ſin and danger of Warre, to incline the hearts of men to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:162107:17"/>embrace, and to quicken the endeavours of men to purſue, Peace? Is it Malignancy, when God hath put into the hands of each ſide a great Sword, and the Land is dayly wounding, diſmembring, and ſo diſgracing, weakening, indangering it ſelfe, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to ſeeke peace by Treaty, and that ſpeedily, ſeeing we periſh dayly? If this be Malignancy, I confeſſe there was ſtore in the Sermon; but Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures muſt be made Apocrypha, and the nature of things inverted, before ſuch leſſons as theſe can be noxious to Church or State. All pretend to Peace, nor will many be ſeene to be againſt the way of Peace by Treaty. I have read an Expreſſion in an Anſwer to a Petition of the Seamen, wherein the Houſe of Commons is ſaid to take notice <hi>of their approbation of the Votes touching a Treaty, for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being for Peace, no good man but deſires it.</hi> If peace be the deſire of all good men, and a Treaty be the readieſt way to effect it, It is the moſt irrationall thing in the world to traduce a Sermon for Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy, wherein that is chiefly aymed at that all good men deſire. But when men are earneſt for Peace, thoſe whoſe guilt or intereſt drawes them another way, to burthen them with prejudice, cry out, they would have Peace on any termes; They would have Peace without Truth: But how untruly and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationally is this objected againſt them that now plead for Peace by Treaty? Being ſo many and great things have been often offered by the King to draw on Treaty in other things, which the preſſers for Peace do generally take for granted, that the King
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:162107:18"/>will ſtill make good, if Treaty on thoſe Offers be granted, but if it ſtill be denyed, and inconveniences follow, I am ſure the preſſers for Treaty would be moſt innocent of thoſe evill conſequences that the Land is like to be endangered with for want of it: And for truth or purity, I know not what cauſe any man hath to ſuſpect the ſincerity or meaſure of my reſpect to either; it being no great ſecret that I have for reſpect to them neglected my owne private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt above this 20. yeares, being continually if not under a ſtorme, yet under a cloud, for adherency to truth and purity. And (me thinkes) any man may very well perceive now, that without Peace we are like to have neither truth, nor holineſſe; No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being a greater blaſting to either than a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Civill War. Who knowes not that Religion hath ever gained by ſuffering, <hi>Sanguis Martyrum, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Eccleſiae, Martyrs Bloud, was the Churches Seed:</hi> But who can tell where it gained by warring? Our experience tells us that when Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> were bound, the Word of God was not bound; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were more converted from nature to Grace, nor was there ever a more ſenſible encreaſe of the power of Godlineſſe, but ſince the Miniſters have been at large, hath not the Word of God been bound? The complaint being generally of the barrenneſſe of the Miniſtry, and but few converted in compariſon of thoſe who are ſcandalized &amp; perverted? And therfore I ſpeak the truth in Chriſt; The main grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that hath moved me to that earneſtneſſe for Accommodation, which I have expreſſed formerly, as well as of late,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:162107:18"/>hath been my tender reſpect to the honour, power and truth of Religion which never ſuffered more by any accident than by this unnaturall War: And if there be not the ſooner an honourable Peace, I am affraid <hi>Conclamatum eſt,</hi> we may hang up our harpes for the exile of Piety, and ſit downe and weepe bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly when we remember our <hi>Sion.</hi> Therfore if pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſute of Peace be deemed Malignancy, I ſhall not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dye in it, but if need be (I hope) dye for it: but other Malignancy (that is truly ſuch) I renownce. Farewell.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
